<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: devops | Charles' Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://ccare.github.com/blog/categories/devops/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ccare.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-23T21:46:25+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ccare.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Charles Care]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Velocity 2011... a great conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://ccare.github.com/blog/2011/06/11/velocity-2011-dot-dot-dot-a-great-conference/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-11T20:27:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ccare.github.com/blog/2011/06/11/velocity-2011-dot-dot-dot-a-great-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s a week now since I came back from
<a href="http://velocityconf.com/velocity2011">O'Reilly&rsquo;s Velocity</a>
conference in San
Jose so I&rsquo;ve had a chance to let some of the thoughts settle in my mind. I
attended both the main conference and the workshops the day before.</p>

<p>Attending a large tech conference is a great way of getting up to speed with the
latest technical themes and meet some great people. Velocity&rsquo;s three days long,
but tacked on the end was DevopsDays &ndash; a more informal meet-up of people
interested in bringing the traditionally separate roles of development and
operations together. Devops was also an important theme at Velocity. Or, as Theo
Schlossnagle said in
his <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y0mHo7SMCQk&amp;feature=player_embedded">Velocity keynote on careers</a>&hellip;
it&rsquo;s really about *ops.
Whatever technology you build, that software&rsquo;s delivering a service, and
whatever that service, it must operate. Or to put it from another way Theo was
saying that we should treat &lsquo;operability like security&rsquo;.</p>

<p>For the last couple of months, I&rsquo;ve been working within the platform team at
<a href="http://www.talis.com">Talis</a>. We&rsquo;re a small team, but have a lot we want to build and manage. Trying to
organise ourselves in a devops is something really important to the way we work.
Personally, I&rsquo;ve never felt comfortable with the traditional &lsquo;throw it over the
wall&rsquo; relationship between software and operations teams. I&rsquo;ve worked in a
number of different kinds of teams before, usually I&rsquo;ve tried to be a developer
who works closely with ops, but I&rsquo;ve definitely fallen into the us and them trap
from time to time. Like agile, devops is not a magic formula, but I definitely
feel much more comfortable with everyone being part of the same team.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve decided to blog some of my thoughts/notes from the conference: the posts
should start to appear very soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
