<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: VisibleOps | Charles' Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://ccare.github.com/blog/categories/visibleops/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ccare.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-09T14:06:16+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ccare.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Charles Care]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Visible Ops]]></title>
    <link href="http://ccare.github.com/blog/2012/03/23/visible-ops/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-23T16:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ccare.github.com/blog/2012/03/23/visible-ops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend I finally got around to reading
the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Visible-Ops-Handbook-Implementing-Practical/dp/0975568612">Visible Ops handbook</a>. I'd
been meaning to read it for a while - ever since I first heard Gene Kim speak at
a conference last year.</p>

<p>All in all it's an interesting read. I didn't find the book particularly
controversial. But, then again, it is nearly 7 years since the book was first
published. I think few people would disagree that many of the practices are
now part of the 'received wisdom' of operations. I also found it useful to get
a reminder of the ITIL jargon. Using the correct terms for this sort of thing
is something I'm a bit weak on, but as the authors say in the book, having a
common language is vital.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Working for a smaller company, I suppose some of the talk about audits and
change-review boards sounded a bit overkill. Although it made me realise that
the natural turn-off of these things is usually more to do with past
experience of bureaucratic processes, rather than a feeling that audit and
change-reviews are, in-themselves, a bad thing.</p>

<p>The other week I gave a <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/cpcare/warwick-2012">lecture</a>
to <a href="http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/dcs/teaching/material/cs321/">students at Warwick</a>
about what it's like to
be a software developer at Kasabi. I had lots of things to talk about:
our product, our team, our culture, etc. However I wanted to share something
about our working practices. The practices we use have certainly evolved over
time, inspired from various methodologies and communities including: Scrum,
Kanban, and dev-ops. However, if I had to choose one thing that I couldn't do
without, I think it would be having a code-review process that's tightly
coupled to the build/release process.</p>

<p>Nearly a year ago, our team moved to
using <a href="http://code.google.com/p/gerrit/">Gerrit</a> as our principle review
tool. The way it integrates with version control and continuous integration is
fantastic. We were already following a continuous deployment model, but I feel
that following the Gerrit workflow has helped us get closer to doing truly
automated deployments. We're also a distributed team, so spending extra-time
on code-reviews can make up for less time spent pair-programming.</p>

<p>So lets return to Visible Ops... for me, one of the biggest take-aways from
reading the book was the idea that the acceptable number of unauthorised
changes should be zero. Two points follow directly from this: 1) that
code-review / change-review should be a straightforward and fast process (so
that it's not routinely circumvented), and 2) that even emergency changes
should go through some kind of review process. In fact, the authors of Visible
Ops make the valid point that emergency changes often benefit from closer
review. For me, the simplicity of using a review-tool (like Gerrit) that's
built into the release process facilitates both of these goals. There have
been times when I've needed to push an emergency fix. But because the tooling
is relatively quick and simple to use, more and more I'm finding that I prefer
to take these changes down the normal review path. Even though we're not doing
heavy-weight audits, from an ITIL perspective, it's re-assuring to know that
these changes are going through a robust, well-understood, and auditable
process.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
