<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Talis | Charles' Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://ccare.github.com/blog/categories/talis/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ccare.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-23T21:55:07+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ccare.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Charles Care]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving on from Talis]]></title>
    <link href="http://ccare.github.com/blog/2012/05/04/moving-on-from-talis/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-04T15:55:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ccare.github.com/blog/2012/05/04/moving-on-from-talis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s all change for me again. I&rsquo;ve decided to move on from <a href="http://talis.com">Talis</a>. Today was my last day in the office, and the end of what has been an
incredible journey. Although it&rsquo;s only just over a year since I joined the Talis Platform team, we&rsquo;ve been constanly iterating and developing
innovative solutions. A year ago, we had the opportunity to focus
entirely on our next generation data platform, and I felt we had a really
productive year. It has certainly been a constant learning-curve for
me and forced me to seriously think about the design and
implementation of distributed systems. Whether it&rsquo;s been about dev-ops, continuous deployment, RDF, Jena, sparql, or zeromq, I don&rsquo;t feel I&rsquo;ve stopped
learning. The pace has been great.</p>

<p>As engineers, I think we all aspire to work on great projects, preferably using cool technology to deliver great software. The last year
has certainly allowed me to do that. However, what really counts is being surrounded by great people &mdash; and that&rsquo;s certainly been true
of working at Talis.
I&rsquo;ve certainly learnt a lot and have really benefited from working with some truly inspirational people.</p>

<p>In a few weeks time I&rsquo;ll be joining the team at <a href="http://blackpepper.co.uk/">Black Pepper software</a>. I&rsquo;m excited about the fresh challenge, but
will definitely miss my old colleagues at Talis.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
